Uh happy Tuesday. Thank you for joining
us. Uh today's webinar u that is being
hosted by agency 1. We're going to talk
about estate planning strategies for
foreign nationals using life insurance
and our featured speaker is coming from
Credential. I hope everybody knows that
I am Kathy Neifeld, a partner with
Agency 1. And Agency 1 is pleased and
delighted and proud to bring you uh
these webinars from our carrier partners
on a regular basis. Today, as I
mentioned, we're going to be talking
about life insurance opportunities and
strategies uh for foreign nationals.
This is a this is a space that has
always interested me uh cuz there's a
lot of different things that are
involved from a tax tax and planning
perspective when dealing with foreign
nationals. It's definitely a specialty
market but it's a market that can be
extremely interesting, rewarding and
lucrative uh when folks uh decide that
this is a space that they want to
concentrate in. Our featured speaker is
Vicente Pina who is the director of
advanced planning at Prudential. Vicente
has over 35 35 years of industry
experience including 15 years in
advanced planning and advanced
marketing. Uh as I mentioned he's a
director on Credential's individual life
insurance advanced planning team. He has
worked predominantly in the develop
development, marketing, distribution and
support of life insurance. His primary
focus at credential is life insurance
planning for the ultra affluent
strategies for high netw worth and
foreign national clients and advanced
case design. I'm going to turn this over
to Vicente. If you have any questions,
please either type them in the chat or
in the Q&A and we will address them as
they are submitted um at an appropriate
time when I feel like it's uh uh timely
to try and interrupt Vicente to deal
with the questions and we'll certainly
open it up for questions at the end. So
without further ado, um Vicente, I'd
like to turn this over to you and thank
you. Thank you Kathy and thank you Lisa,
thank you Gonzalo, thank you Agency 1
and my colleague Lenny Paul for putting
this all together and um uh this is an
exciting market. Part of it is because I
was a foreign national uh I worked for
many years in our industry in Asia and
Latin America. um worked in uh
everywhere from Taiwan to Hong Kong to
Singapore, South Korea, uh Philippines,
as well as most of South America. And um
so we're going to get into this as Kathy
said, um ask any questions. You're
actually going to find that this market
is not as much a niche as it used to be.
It's actually becoming a major part of
the market. There's uh data out there
from the US Census Bureau that 25% of
all households in the United States have
at least one person born in another
country. Uh so just think about your
neighborhood, think about the people you
went to college with, think about the
people you work with. Uh many of them
came from elsewhere. They all didn't
just, you know, um born right here in,
you know, your hometown, right? So So
think about that and think about um
advisors who are working this market. Um
and also advisors who live in places
like the you know DC, New York um any
metropolitan area where there are people
who uh were born elsewhere frankly and
that's just uh that's a a tremendous
market and they have the same needs that
most others u insurance people who need
insurance have. So uh we have several
pieces um Lisa will send these out to
you. This happens to be one of our
PowerPoint decks that uh that we have.
Um but I'm going to um go kind of more
into the um the details of the market,
how to write this kind of business. And
so I'm going to switch out of this and
I'm going to get into one of our um our
PDFs that uh that we have available. And
it it basically is a more of a um
strategizing document for going after
this market. And so when we talk about
um foreign nationals, we're really
talking about two types of individuals.
They are individuals who were born in
another country but now live here
full-time and people who are born
elsewhere but they only come here
periodically. So uh as I said you know
earlier the foreignb born population is
is huge. It's uh uh you know 26%
uh of the children under 18 in the US
have at least one immigrant parent. It's
just I mean look at my own neighborhood.
I live in a little culde-sac here in
Beaverton, Oregon. And you know there's
a Filipino woman married to an American
guy. There's a Colombian guy married to
an American woman. Um you know so it's
there's a guy from the Dominican
Republic uh married to an American
woman. So it's it's it's it's huge. Now,
part of it is, think about the employers
in the area where I live. Nike is the
largest employer, probably the like
largest employer in Oregon. Uh, but also
Intel is a is a huge um employer and
they're bringing in people from Europe.
They're bringing people from Latin
America. They're bringing people from
Asia to work here. And so I, you know,
there's so many foreign nationals around
my neighborhood. Uh, they just I see
them when I go out for lunch. They're
walking around the neighborhood. They're
kind of like for those of you that have
been to Europe or to Latin America, it's
kind of they're just going for a walk at
lunchtime and you see and there many of
them are, you know, uh chatting and
talking and catching up. So, uh it's all
around us. Um and particularly, I would
say in in certainly in the DC area for
obvious reasons. So, um as I said,
there's there's two groups. Uh there's
the non-resident alien and the resident
alien. And again, the only difference is
one is living here, the resident alien.
They're living here. So, they were born
in another country, but they're living
here full-time. The good news about that
market is that's regular business.
Regular business. You don't have to do
anything special. You have a uh you
know, an a client or maybe you have a
prospect or maybe have a an advisor who
you know has uh clients or prospects
that were born in other countries, but
they live here. They go to they have
their kids go to school with your kids,
their kids. Those those folks, those
resident aliens, it's normal business.
Nothing special. You could write them
today. Nothing special. The non-resident
aliens are folks who were born
elsewhere, but they come here
periodically, you know, say three or
four months a year. The example I like
to use is you have a lot of Europeans
that come to say Florida in the
wintertime. I can remember going to a
spring training game in Tampa and um
actually in Deneden and uh went to see a
Toronto Blue Jays games and 90% of the
people in the stands were Canadians. Now
those Canadians are coming down to
Florida in the winter time. They're
going to see the Blue Jays, the Red Sox.
They're going to enjoy, you know, the
whatever the nice weather, but you know,
they're not here full-time. They live in
Canada, but they come down for a month
or two or three. Those non-resident
aliens, there's an opportunity there as
well. Now, there are some requirements,
some more hoops to go through. Um, but
we can still write them depending on the
country that they're coming from. And
we'll get into that uh that country um
you know, the countries that perhaps uh
are more attractive u to you and I and
to insurance companies in other
countries. So, now that we've
established they're into two groups,
resident aliens is easy business.
Nothing you got to do special.
Non-resident alien requires a little bit
more work. Um, but we're going to go
into that and it's pretty
straightforward. In terms of the
similarities, they have the same needs
that everyone on this call has, right?
If they're married, they have income
replacement, uh, salary continuation.
They certainly want to leave something
for their heirs. Um, you know, most of
these folks have a really big, um,
concentration of focus on making sure
their kids go to college. It's kind of a
cultural thing. And so they definitely
want to make sure they have enough
insurance to help their kids pay
through, you know, pay college and have
it paid completely by um some mechanism
like life insurance. Uh eliminating
debts. We all want to eliminate debts
and of course they're no different. I
would say a lot of foreign nationals
really don't like credit. They don't
like to, you know, have a lot of debt
because in their home countries they're
typically not incurring a lot of debt.
So certainly playing up getting rid of
the debt, getting rid of the mortgage,
getting rid of the credit cards. Um
that's that's a big uh selling factor.
And last but really not least is there's
an estate tax angle particularly for
non-resident aliens. And we'll get into
this, but um if you think about
non-resident aliens, they most of their
assets are outside of the US. Let's be
honest, right? you live uh in France um
and you uh have a home maybe or
apartment in the DC area, maybe your
children married Americans and now you
come to visit because your grandkids are
uh in the local area. Well, you know,
you're here 2, three months a year, but
your assets in the US are subject to
estate tax and the exemption amount um
is only anyone know, you could type it
in the chat. It's only
$60,000. There we go. Somebody did
mention it in the chat and uh they did
60. Great job. Uh so 60,000. So what
does that mean? That means that if you
own assets in the UI, US more than
60,000, which is almost anything, you
know, it's it's basically a car, maybe
a, you know, certainly your home. I
don't think you can buy a home in the US
anymore for $60,000. Any asset you own
in the US that's over 60,000 is subject
to US federal estate tax. Most
non-resident aliens don't know that
because that kind of tax regime doesn't
exist in their country. It's unfamiliar
uh to them. And so that's going to
that's going to be a another kind of
motivating factor for them to buy life
insurance life insurance particularly if
they're successful, right? Think about
the non-resident alien maybe that has a
million-doll apartment in the DC area or
maybe they buy an apartment for their
kid or their, you know, their
daughter-in-law, son-in-law and their
and their spouse and and their family.
Or maybe they buy a home next to the
grandkids. Um so therefore there that's
an aspect that they're not aware of that
you'll be aware of and you'll be able to
help them. The resident aliens um
they're treated like everyone on this
call. They're taxed on their worldwide
assets which is kind of a a good and
bad. It's bad from the standpoint that
most resident aliens are not aware that
they're taxed on their worldwide assets.
meaning, you know, their home in France,
their home in Taiwan, their home in uh
China for that matter. Um, if you're a
resident alien, you're taxed on your
worldwide assets. Now, the the kind of
maybe positive part of that is they do
share in that
$13.99 million exemption that we all
have at the federal level. Many of you
know that uh we we have a an exemption
at the federal level of about $14
million. So, we'll get more into that.
But again, another takeaway is that
there is an estate tax angle to working
with particularly successful high netw
worth affluent non-resident aliens and
resident aliens. As I said, there's some
differences. Um, you know, uh, some
cultures rep, uh, you know, embrace life
insurance, some don't. Some countries
have life insurance, but the face amount
is quite small. I can remember working
in Argentina and working in in Brazil um
and you know even in Colombia uh you
know the face amounts that they can get
are fairly low relative to what we can
get in the US and then on top of that
they'd like the US dollar let's be
honest it you know the currency in other
countries tend to fluctuate remember
working in Argentina back in the early
2000s and they went through five
presidents in a matter of uh several
months and the currency was devalued ed
several times. They actually changed
their currency a number of times and so
um it's really for the high net worth
and the successful um you know resident
alien or non-resident alien they would
prefer to buy their insurance in the US
for lots of reasons not the least of
which is certainly our economy and our
currency is fairly stable. Um, we talked
a little bit about non-resident aliens.
You know, again, they're not US citizens
because they were born elsewhere and
they're not primarily living here. They
come here maybe, you know, 2, three,
four months a year. They may own a home
here. They may own a business. I know in
different parts of the country, um, they
may have, uh, you know, they may own a
business. They may be a passive owner in
a business or, as I said, they may own
real estate here. Now, as we said, high
net worth and affluent non-residents,
you know, they know what their home
country risks are, and it's almost like
a, you know, we hear about the
non-correlated asset. Well, here's a
non-correlated risk their home country.
They've got, uh, assets in the US that
they want to protect. They have
insurance that they know isn't going to
fluctuate or get devalued um, in like
their home country currency. Um there
are some tax issues in some cases um
with you know with assets owned in the
US versus assets owned um elsewhere. Uh
we don't and you know at PUR don't
really get into the income tax aspects
of it. Um but certainly you know we're
going to pay the death benefit income
tax-free. So that's an important thing.
So, when I wrote this piece, um, I was
kind of thinking about an example. And
so, I I went down here and I had this
woman, uh, in just in my mind, uh,
Christina. I made her up, a non-resident
alien, and she's doiciled in China. Now,
I only picked China because China and
Mexico tend to be the two of the more
common countries we see business from,
but we do see it from the UK. We see it
from Germany. Uh we see it from Italy,
we see it from uh other countries, but I
would say China and Mexico are probably
the two more common. And anyway, she
comes to the US to visit family and
friends. She went to college here. Uh
maybe she went to GW like I did. And she
also comes here for business. She's a
successful executive. And of course,
when you come to the US that often, it
just makes sense at some point, well,
you know, I may as well establish a bank
account here. That way, I can do, you
know, any kind of business I want. And
she decided, I'm going to buy a condo um
here on the East Coast in New York. And
so, you know, it gives her a little bit
of a footprint here. She doesn't have to
go to a hotel every time. Doesn't have
to worry about transaction fees with
her, you know, international bank
account back home in China. She just has
a regular bank account here and a home
here. She doesn't live there year round.
Um, but she's there, you know, maybe two
or three months a year. Her assets in
the US are subject to federal estate
tax. So, let's be conservative. That
condominium in New York City might cost
a million dollars. Well, with a $60,000
exemption and a 40% tax, federal estate
tax, I mean, basically that whole uh
condominium is going to be subject to
estate tax. So, if she were to die 9
months later, that estate tax is due,
federal estate tax, and it's 40%. So,
her estate, maybe her family, um maybe
she's got a partner, that person or the
executive is going to have to basically
sell that to pay the tax because 40% of
940,000 is still 300 and some odd
thousand. and 300 somehat thousand um
unless she has that in her bank account,
it's going to be uh that's going to what
has to be paid to the IRS. So that's
just a simple example of someone just
owns one asset in the US um and that
asset is is significant. It's certainly
more than
$60,000. Um I mentioned a little bit
about income tax. You know, we probably
on the life insurance side of our
business don't talk a lot about income
tax other than obviously the death
benefit being income taxfree. We all
know a cash value grows without any tax.
You can take withdrawals. There's no
difference in the product. Uh let's just
put that right out there. You sell them
a credential permanent insurance policy.
It's not going to be any different than
if one of us on this call bought that
same product. I will say the government
does track how long you're in the US. Um
there's a reason why we go through
security and um we go through homeland
security because they can track how many
days you are in the US just like they
can track how many days I was in France
recently cuz when you go into the
country um they have that data and when
you leave the country and the same thing
in the US they know how long. So you
might have some clients who might be
here six months and they're kind of
bordering. And so if they're a resident
and they fall on the resident side, then
it makes the whole process of selling
them life insurance much easier. If
they're on the kind of the the, you
know, underside of that, say 138 days or
less, then they'd be considered a
non-resident. Again, we don't get
involved in a substantial presence test,
but just be aware that the government is
watching how long clients are here,
prospects are here, all of us are here.
Um, and so, um, I would say most of the
cases we see, they're very heavily
weighted one way or the other. They're
either, you know, clearly non-residents.
They're here for a month or two. Like I
said, they go to Florida, maybe they go
to Arizona, maybe they go to Disney
World with their kids, that kind of
thing. but they're clearly only here for
a short amount of time, relatively
speaking, or they're just residents.
They're here all the time, and then they
go visit maybe their home country, but
they're here all the time. Uh, we get a
lot of questions about visas, and it's
really not important for us from the
visa standpoint, from an underwriting
perspective. And what I mean by that is
we pay attention from an underwriting
perspective to residency. We want to
know where do they live? Why do we want
to know where they live? because that's
where all their medical information is.
You know, if I live in France and I have
a French doctor, I have a French
pharmacy, I have that, or if I live in
China, all of that. Uh, but if I live
in, you know, the DC area, I live in
Maryland, uh, but I'm from France or I'm
from China, well, my medical records and
all my underwriting, my my motor vehicle
record, my driver's license, all of that
is right there in Maryland or right
there in DC. So, um, that's wonderful
because that means it's easier to get
that medical information. So, we pay
attention more to residency than
citizenship. We pay more attention to
residency than visas, per se. Now, um,
I'm going to talk a little bit about the
estate tax. I think we we we we we
touched on it earlier. Um there's uh
certainly um you know they want to know
the government wants to know where
you're primarily doiciled and and where
you're primarily doiciled determines the
assets that are included in your estate.
So without going into a lot of depth
suffice it to say that if you're
doiciled in the US like most of us on
this call everything that we own is
pretty much included in our estate for
state tax purposes. For the non-resident
it's just the assets that they own in
the US. um it could be a house, it could
be a car, could be bank accounts, all
those things would be included in their
estate. Now, um there are some rules.
We're not going to get into them uh
today, but there are some differences
between gifting between US residents and
US citizens. there's some minor type of
differences but the most important thing
I feel is going to be this slide here
which is talking about or this page um
what is uh the impact of a person being
a US citizen and their estate tax. So if
you're a single person you know your
estate tax today exemption is 13.99
million that's straightforward. If
you're married to a US citizen, like
many of us probably are on this call, um
well, we get two of those, right? We get
13.99 and 13.99. That's your classic
estate planning case, your eyelet case
that many of us work on. Now, when
you're married to a resident alien or
non-resident alien or you have a
resident alien married to a US citizen,
all these different combinations, it
does
matter who dies first. So let's take an
example of say you're a you know
resident alien married to a US citizen.
Well that US citizen gets the 13.99 as
does a resident alien. But let's say
you're a resident alien and you're
married to a non-resident alien. Well
the resident alien gets the 13.99 but
the non-resident would only get that
$60,000 exemption. And then lastly,
you've got the non-resident alien
married to these different, you know, US
citizen resident alien or non-resident
alien. Um, again, the $60,000 is the big
issue. So, when you have these upper
ones, I was in this circumstance when I
got married. My wife was a resident
alien. She'd been living in the US for
probably 20 or 30 years, but then um
decided in 2016 to become a US citizen.
Well, now you know we went from, you
know, kind of US citizen married to
resident alien or resident alien married
US citizen, right? Depending on if I
died first or she died first. There are
implications here. But now that she's a
US citizen and I'm a US citizen, I was
always a US citizen. We get all the
perks that a US citizen gets. So, what's
the takeaway from this page? One, when
you are a resident alien, you're taxed
on your worldwide assets. We remember
that. um you do get this 13.99
exemption, but it does matter who you're
married to. So, if you're married to a
non-resident alien, you don't get the
estate tax marital deduction, which
means, you know, assets can go back and
forth between uh spouses. As many of you
know, you know, there's no gifting
between spouses. There's no issues
because, you know, the government
recognizes that a married couple can
just give each other money and gifts all
the time. They don't need to report
that, right? they're they're kind of one
financial unit when it comes for that
kind of thing. But when you're a
resident alien, married to a resident
alien or a non-resident, there's this uh
qualified domestic trust that they call
that they refer to that can preserve
some of that estate tax marital
deduction. But in the real world or a
more, you know, logical solution is life
insurance because this person is going
to have to create this trust with their
attorney. And what they're really doing
is creating a situation where they have
some liquidity at that first person's
death. Well, with life insurance, we all
know the liquidity is there 3 or 4 days
after you die. So, an alternative to a Q
dot would be buying life insurance
either at the first death or the second
death. So, um we're going to get into
the countries in a moment. Um, but uh I
do want to just kind of talk a little
bit about writing this business. Um, so
we're gonna, you know, kind of get into
the life insurance because when you have
a non-resident alien, um, like I said,
there's more hoops to join through to
jump through. So again, non-resident
alien is basically someone who spends
more than six months a year outside of
the US or they may also have dual
residency, but their primary residence
is outside of the US. Um, so I have an
example here of a a Swedish citizen who
owns a home in Sweden and lives in the
US for less than 6 months a year for
businesses purposes. So that that person
would be considered a Swedish resident.
Um, some people be aware are in the
process of becoming a US citizen or
getting a green card or so on and so
forth, but the time that you're writing
the app, they might be considered a non
US resident. Bear that in mind. Even
though they haven't gotten to the point
where they're a US resident, if you
write them today and they're a non- US
resident, that's what you have to write
them. You can't assume the underwriters
are going to say, "Well, in six months
from now they'll be a resident." Well,
in six months from now, then you write
the app. Um, in terms of the application
itself, everything has to be done in the
US. I know Gonzalo would love to send
all of you over abroad uh and pay for
you to write applications, but that's
not reality. That's fantasy land. Um, so
the whole aspects of the insurance
transaction must be completed in the US
from solicitation to policy delivery.
So, you've got that prospect. Maybe
they're from Europe or South America,
Africa, or Latin America or uh Asia, and
they come to the US maybe 2, three
months a year. That's when you write
them because you're not going to fly to
China to write them. We know that. Um
so, we do want to see some type of
nexus, meaning, you know, what's their
connection to the US. It just can't be
an arbitrary person visiting. um you
know obviously if they're a US citizen
and they're living abroad they're still
considered a non-resident right because
if they're living in China and they're
American citizen they're still
considered non-resident but that nexus
has been satisfied or their spouse is a
US citizen or a US resident. We see that
a lot with China. Maybe one spouse is an
executive in a Chinese company maybe or
a company doing business in China and
then they have one spouse in the US
perhaps raising the children or with the
grandparents or that kind of thing. Um
or they own you real estate in the US.
That's an easy nexus, right? I own a
home in you know the DC area and I'm
from Africa or South America. Well, that
that checks the box of having a nexus.
If you're employed by a US company, um
you have a US tax liability. We talked
about that the estate tax. We do like to
see um and these are any of these are
okay. Now, you don't need to require all
of these, but if they have ownership of
US assets for a minimum of 6 months and
equal to 25% of their net worth or a
minimum 500,000, meaning let's say they
don't they don't um satisfy any of these
other arrows, these bullets above um but
they have, you know, US assets uh with a
minimum of 500,000. I would say most of
you probably have prospects who have
that, right? I mean, a home in the DC
area is going to be worth more than a
half a million dollars. So, you've
already checked that box. So, um, think
of this as just being kind of an
entrylevel kind of, uh, requirement. Any
nexus to the US, any of these, not all
of them, just one of them is fine. We
find, particularly in the the banks and
the wirehouses that this is easy because
they're usually managing money or have
clients who are worth a lot more than a
half a million dollars. So think of this
as pretty straightforward, pretty easy
to satisfy. One thing that does come up
is this EB5 visa program. This is a fast
track to becoming getting a green card
and eventually becoming a US citizen.
The government a number of years ago
said, "Hey, if you're a foreign person
and you come to the US and you start a
business and you hire Americans and you
have Americans on payroll, uh, we're
going to fasttrack you for a green card.
You're going to jump ahead in the line."
So if you are aware of any clients or
prospects of the EB5 visa, perhaps you
network with attorneys or immigration
people and they are aware of people with
EB5 visas. That's a perfect market
because obviously they're here in the
US. They're creating jobs. The
government loves them. Credential loves
them. So any type of EB5 visa individual
um that looks really good because it
implies they're creating businesses and
jobs in the US. uh will issue pretty
much any age. Um you know uh young
people gets a little bit weird because
you know you don't want to insure a
10-year-old for $100 million. That looks
a little odd. Um and that's that would
be the same in the US, right? Um so
usually we see people in their 20s to
their 70s. Um the minimum face is 250.
The more the average face on the foreign
national is closer to $4 million. So
people that we see applying are applying
for big face amounts. It's typically
permanent, although term is available as
well. We don't really care what product
they want to buy. TERM, they want to buy
survivorship, they want to buy um, you
know, any type of VUL, IL, all of it is
available. Um, so that's good because we
we don't have a a different category of
products. So, let's get into Gonzalo's
question. So, you got a non-resident,
right? And he or she tells you or tells
the producer, "Hey, I'm from XYZ
country. that's where I predominantly
live. Well, we want to know where they
predominantly live because there's some
countries, let's be honest, that are
more risky than others. And what I mean
by that is think about um somebody maybe
who is in a war torn country or a
country that's having severe economic
problems. Um your life expectancy, let's
be honest, is going to be affected by a
war torn country that you live in. You
might come to the US a month for a
month, but you're going back to that war
torn country or you're going back to
that economically difficult country. So
like most carriers, we split these
countries into categories A, B, and C.
And A is all these countries here, which
means preferred best. You can write them
isn't um you know any issue. Um it's a
mix of countries from you know Europe,
Asia, Latin America. Um certainly um
plenty of uh countries here. B countries
are countries that you the best we can
get is non-smoker plus. And then there's
a whole mix of countries here in the
middle kind of in the yellow that you
know some of the urban areas are A like
most of China uh the urban areas are A.
Some of the more uh say suburban uh
smaller somewhat smaller cities are B
and then the absolute rural areas are C
meaning they're not acceptable. But you
have areas like Colombia um that have B
and C. Ecuador is a mix of A and B. So
one of the key questions you want to ask
or at least find out when you're in this
market is where is this individual again
a non-resident where do they primarily
live? They live in Sweden, no problem.
If they live in India, you're going to
want to know are they in, you know,
Kolkata, Delhi, are they in Mumbai? uh
if they're not in one of those major
regions, then then it's going to be a
little harder because uh those sea
regions, those rural areas are not
acceptable. And rural obviously means,
you know, there's rural medicine,
there's probably rural care, and it's a
lot harder to issue a case when people
live out in the rural areas where
medical information and medical service,
frankly, is much harder. Um I mentioned
Mexico. We see lots of business here.
Most of Mexico, the big cities are A and
the rest of it is B. So, if you have any
Mexican prospects, it's a great market,
as is Peru as well. So, I'm going to
just take a moment here and stop, see if
there's any questions so far. I I think
I see some in the chat, but I wasn't
sure if anyone had answer them or if
you'd like me to answer them.
Um, Vicente
um, oh, one of them was what are the
requirements regarding the medical exam
and where it needs to take place? Yes.
All in the US. So, what typically
happens, Kathy, is let's say I'm that
individual, right? And you're writing me
or one of your producers is writing me.
I land in DC or I land in New York and
I'm going to be here for a month
visiting my kids or maybe I'm going to a
college reunion, right? And I'm going to
be here for a month. Well, then what I
would do is I'd get together with my
advisor after I check into my hotel or
my Airbnb and you write the application
right there. Then you schedule, maybe
you did this already, you schedule the
pyramid maybe uh you know for next week
or the end of the week and then the bare
pyramid comes to my hotel Airbnb or
whatever. um and any requirements I
have. So, you're going to do that during
their visit for the non-resident and
then hopefully by the time they leave
the policyy's issued. Now, obviously, if
they're going to come here for 3 days,
you're not going to get the policy
issued. I don't think anybody's going to
expect that. But if they're going to be
here for a month or 6 weeks or or you
know, uh 2 months, 3 months, then I
would say write the application uh
shortly after they arrive and then we'll
get all the medical information and
hopefully we'll get it issued by time
they leave. So, that's a good question.
We have a lot of firms around the
country who specialize in this market.
So, they it's almost like a concierge
service. They make sure the client, you
know, as soon as they're settled into
their hotel or their Airbnb, they've got
the application, the advisers there, um,
and they meet with them. They take the
application and they submit it. Uh maybe
they even do an informal with some you
know basic information so that Lenny uh
can get the uh you know underwriters
involved and get the ball rolling so
that by time you take the formal
application maybe you know 70% of the
work has been done. Um there are some
countries and I think Gonzalo was uh uh
you know um uh kind of referring to this
in his question. There are some
countries that are just very uh
difficult for us to issue policy to
their residents. It's because they have
laws that prevent their residents from
buying life insurance. So uh Argentina,
Italy, Japan are three prominent
examples. Um and if you're a Japanese
resident, um Japan says it's against the
law for their residents to buy life
insurance from a non-Japanese carrier.
It's against the law. So credential is
not going to break the law to write a
Japanese resident. We're not going to
break the law to write an Italian
resident or an Argentinian resident.
Now, if they come here, the Japanese
resident, and they move here, and they
live here, and they become a resident of
the US, no problem. We see that a lot
with Japanese residents moving to
Hawaii. And so what they'll do is
they'll spend maybe seven months, eight
months a year in Hawaii and then two to
three months back in Japan. that's fine
because their primary residence is
Hawaii. But if their primary residence
is Japan or Italy or Ireland or any of
these countries on this gray list here,
we cannot write them because we would be
breaking the law and credential cannot
break the law to issue a policy. Um
South Africa by the way um you know we
we certainly do the bigger uh cities
like Cape Town, Johannesburg and Ptoria
and they're A they get preferred best.
All the other areas are B. There are
some countries in this C section here
that are just the risk is too big. Now,
for example, um Israel stands out
because Israel was always an A, but with
what's happened over the last couple of
years, we temporarily put them into C,
but for the last 25 years, Israel has
been an A. So, I think as things get
better there, you'll see them go back to
A. But for now, they're there. So
countries that are on this list are here
some of them for a long time because
they're, you know, like Russia, you
know, or Syria. They're going to be
there for the se foreseeable future just
because of the issues there, the war
there. We have government, US government
sanctions against those countries. So
certainly you're not going to run a
right business for somebody who
primarily lives in North Korea. Now, if
somebody um you know is living in Israel
for the time being, we can't. But if
they we things improve there and they go
back to being an A country or a B
country then you can write them. But
think of these countries as being
countries we just can't write residents
because of the risk. And so uh let me
ask you this. the these country lists um
within the diff with the different
categories. Is this uniform for all of
the carriers that are in the foreign
national marketplace or for example um
could credential uh write a country that
perhaps one of your competitors would
not or vice versa? Um it's possible
certainly possible Kathy I think one of
the reasons why it's possible is because
this this is a living document. We're
updating this document. We used to
update it every year and a half. We've
been updating it lately every year. In
some cases in Israel, we did it in the
middle of the year. Um, so it could be
that a country that was, you know, on
this list here is now moved because
things have improved. For example, I
know for many years Colombia was really
risky, right? Because of all the issues
that they have with the, you know, with
the terrorists and the and, you know,
the guerillas. and now all of a sudden
Colombia is relatively okay. Um so other
carriers hard to say because I know that
they're also trying to comply with the
government restrictions. So I would say
Kathy for example the Sudan or Syria is
and Russia are going to uh and North
Korea are going to uh exist on every
list of every carrier but there may be
some subtle differences with some of
these smaller countries you know like
Fiji or you know Cambodia. It's it's
hard to say, but we do do an analysis of
the other carriers. Um, but to be honest
with you, 90% of the business probably
comes from about six to eight countries.
So, you you may run into a case once in
a while from Iran or from Honduras, but
that's not going to be the majority of
the cases, right? That'll be the kind of
the oneoff. So, very good question. Um,
so the big takeaway here is you've
established you have a non-resident
alien either as a prospect or a client.
And now you're going to reference this
list to see where they are at. And if
they're um, you know, here under the
sea, you know, you can't write them. If
they're under this gray area, it's
against the law for us to write them.
But if they're anywhere in this kind of
uh uh orang-ish yellow or under the this
kind of teal or under this uh darker
gray A B or this area here, they're
they're you can write them as long as um
they're not in a in a C region.
And of course, if you have any questions
regarding whether or not the country is
acceptable, reach out to uh agency 1 and
we will um share that information with
uh Vicente and his colleagues at PRO and
they'll come back to us with a
definitive yes or no. Absolutely.
Absolutely, Kathy. So, what I wanted to
wrap up with now is, you know, we kind
of know the the, you know, the game
plan. We know that if they're resident
aliens, it's normal business. Okay, we
can just put that one to bed. Um,
uh, the the the uh the non-resident
business, we need to reference what
country they're in, right? Um, so I I
see Gonzalo had a question. I'll just
backtrack and and talk about uh Puerto
Rico. One of the issues with Puerto Rico
is Puerto Rico is not part of the
NIC. So, they don't have to follow some
of the same product rules. For example,
uh my recollection from having worked
there back in the '9s, there's no such
thing as a mech in Puerto Rico. Now,
obviously, in the 50 states, there is
such thing as a mech. So, how do
insurance companies deal with that? They
got to have, you know, Puerto Rico
products or are they going to have US
products? And many carriers do have
Puerto Rico products, but you can't sell
the US mainland product to the Puerto
Rican resident. You have to sell the
Puerto Rican product. So, Puerto Rico
has its own insurance rules, and so some
of them are very advantageous. So, if
you're a Puerto Rican resident,
certainly you may want to look at a
Puerto Rican product, but we do have
some Puerto Rican residents who have
homes in Florida and they would prefer
the US mainland product. So they'll buy
the US main product as long as there are
residents of Florida. If they spend 90%
of their time in Puerto Rico and only
10% of their time in Florida, in our
world, they're considered a Puerto Rican
resident and therefore they should be
buying a Puerto Rican product. We don't
get a lot of business from uh Puerto
Rico for that reason because I think
many of the advisers there, there's
certainly a lot of career companies
there um and they pretty much are able
to handle that market. But we do have
some folks who um who do have, you know,
a home in Florida and uh and they try to
spend as much time there as possible and
therefore they could be considered US
residents. So, good question. Um so,
getting back to writing this business,
okay, you want to get the process going.
Um we like to see that the insured has a
global net worth of 2 million. Now, you
know, you might be asking yourself,
well, why that? Well, you know, we're
really not in the non-resident alien
market to sell, you know, $100,000 term
policies, right? I mean, that that's a
whole different market. Um, we really
want to be in that higher face, you
know, higher net worth market. Now, a
global net worth of 2 million is not a
lot if you think about it because if
they're coming to the US to visit, uh,
they probably have money. Uh, they have
a home back in their home country. They
may have a home here. Uh, they may have
bank accounts here. So, we like to see a
global net worth of $2 million. This is
easy to satisfy if you're working with
advisers in again the banks, the
warehouses, that kind of thing or
certainly the high net work market. Um,
we talked about that nexus which is
really easy that you know usually the
one that they can satisfy is that
$500,000
um of assets in the US. Usually that's
easy. That could be like I said your
home for that matter. You pretty much
check that box. Um, we do have some
paperwork disclosure forms. We don't
need to really get into that. Um, one
question that does often come up is,
hey, they don't have a social security
number. We don't require a social
security number. Credential doesn't
require a social security number.
Frankly, most non-residents don't have
it. Why would a non-resident want to pay
it to a social security system that
they're not going to get any money out
of? Right? If I lived in whatever some
foreign country and I came here for a
month or two, I don't want any pay any
social security taxes because I'm not
going to get any social security because
I'm a non-resident. So, but 99% of
non-residents have a tax ID or what they
call a TIN. And a TIN is a tax ID
number. And it usually in the form of a
W8. A W8 can be accessed, you can get
one in about 30 seconds on the internet.
Um, and it usually there's different
types. The W8 Ben is the most common
that we see. And most non-residents have
this because they want to be able to
deposit a check. They want to be able to
buy a home. They want to be able, you
know, just the basic stuff. You just
can't walk into a bank and not have a
tax ID number and expect to cash a
check, right? They they want something.
So, usually they have some type of uh
tax ID number, and any of these will
suffice.
So, we're heading down the home stretch
here. Um, for the most part, um, you're
going to try to get as much information
prior to them visiting, right? Right.
You can certainly get their height and
weight, you know, uh, you know, find out
where their parents live or where their
parents died, what their parents died
from. You know, try to kind of do that
field underwriting before they even get
here. You probably already know their
ages and their dates of birth.
Obviously, you know their names. Um, so
you can try to get that going. Um, in
some cases we'll require an APS for
people over 50. Um, sometimes we'll, you
know, do the blood test and E ECGs. Um,
we will want some kind of data ver
verification, meaning we're not going to
just assume verbally that they're worth
2 million. You got to have some data
that proves that they're worth 2
million. And again, in most of the
channels, that's fairly easily. Um, if
they had a US driver's license, we'll
want that, their MVR. Um, that's pretty
common. It's common for all US insured
like those of us on this call today.
They would order a
MVR. And then lastly, um uh when it
comes to China, um sometimes we can work
with they had an exam, a US consulate
exam in the last two years. Um we don't
see as much of that now because China
seems to be clamping down on that. So
folks just come to the US and get that
done. Um we we don't really accept
medical information in another language.
Um so you know you send us a you know
documents or they send you documents in
Chinese that's hard underwriting
documents. So we we that's why we rely
so much on the visit right somebody
mentioned earlier in one of the
questions you know h how does this work?
Well, we're going to rely heavily on the
the paramed and the visit, right? So,
you know, when they do their height and
weight and when they take their blood
pressure and anything like that, um
they're going to rely heavily on that
because it's hard to rely on, you know,
Chinese, you know, characters when the
underwriters can't read that and they
don't understand that. Now, if the
client wants to get that stuff
translated um and sent to us, certainly
we'll take it. But, uh we're going to
rely pretty much heavily on what is done
here in the US. Um, terms of, uh,
submitting the application, certainly,
you know, you're going to want to make
sure that, um, you know, you've worked
with Lenny and kind of done some of that
pre pre-claring work with with Kathy and
Lisa and Gonzalo. Just, you know,
anything that you can do to kind of
clear the path so that once you submit
the application, it goes through, you
know, even more smoothly uh, than uh, if
it's all just at once for the first
time. I talked about the face amount uh,
for non-residents is 250. As I said, the
average we get is about 4 million. So
certainly we can go higher than that. I
think we can go up to about 25 million.
Um, Vicente, are those uh are those
limits locked in stone? So if somebody
wanted a little less, is that a
discussion that would be worth having
with you? Um, I don't know if there's an
exception. I don't know if the system
Kathy will take less than a 250 phase to
be honest with you. Um so um uh but
certainly um you know we don't see those
very often but if someone wanted a
smaller face then unfortunately we you
know I'm not aware that we've issued any
face amounts below 250. Now 250 of term
is going to be pretty inexpensive. So
even there as you can imagine there's
not a lot of you know business and and
money to be made there but if it's an
accommodation certainly we we will do
that but below 250 is harder. The bigger
issue that we have is some of the bigger
face amounts on some of these other
regions. So that's, you know, you start
getting into, you know, the A, B, and C
regions and you get into rating classes.
And as you can imagine, somebody rated
who lives in a rural area is not going
to live as long as someone who's not
rated who lives in, you know, London or,
you know what I mean, a major
metropolitan area. Um, one thing I'll
add that's a little bit of an
idiosyncrasy is Canada. We can write
Canadian residents but we cannot write
VUL. And the reason for that is because
Canadian the country of Canada considers
VUL not to be insurance. They consider
it to be an investment first and
foremost an investment. In the United
States a VUL product is considered to be
insurance first and investment product
second. But in Canada it's the other way
around. So again we don't do VUL for
Canadian residents. But if they come
down here and you want to sell them IL,
you want to sell them UL, NLG, you want
to sell them um survivorship IL,
survivorship UL, no problem. But if you
want to sell them VUL, uh we cannot do
it because again they consider that to
be an investment and not insurance. So
the last thing I'll just wrap up with is
how to go after this market. Um, you
know, certainly you, you know, those of
you that live in some of the urban areas
and the suburban areas, uh, around the
country or certainly in the DC, Maryland
area, it's perfect. I mean, think about
the immigration there. I bet you this, I
mean, you know, it's probably more like
30, 40, 50% of households probably have
at least one person born outside of the
US. Um so your normal in networking
marketing you know either through uh
your uh centers of influence um lots of
people meet you know parents through
school my my kids go to an international
school uh international public school
and almost I'd say 80 to 90% of the kids
their parents were born elsewhere um and
so that's just the perfect market. Um,
think about your clients who might be
attorneys or your centers of influence
who deal with immigration. A lot of
business there. They pay a lot of
attorneys, a lot of fees to get their
immigration paperwork going. And
certainly those referrals are perfect.
Uh, I think of like business networking
international like BNI or the Chamber of
Commerce. Um, those are certainly great
places to network. Um, real estate
agents know everything. I mean, you
know, it's funny. That's their business.
They know everything about everybody.
And of course, part of their job is
their networking, too. They want to sell
houses to these newly immigrated
Americans and their newly immigrated
individuals. So, certainly real estate
agents, uh, tax advisors, CPAs, um, any
type of business owner, uh, very common.
Uh I know just in my travels a lot of
South Koreans tend to or own a lot of
businesses that self-employment is kind
of part of their DNA particularly you
know some of the service businesses. So
certainly that's an opportunity there.
Um, if you think about uh folks who
perhaps um you're doing business with
already um and maybe you haven't
actually approached them because you
felt well gee this person was born in
Colombia and I don't even want to go
down that road because I don't know
enough about Colombia. Um or take this
example here of Andrew. Uh he's a
financial professional in Los Angeles
and there's a a Taiwanese community. Um
and he goes to this community with his
family. Um and um he meets Janette
um whose primary residence is in Taiwan.
She happens to be visiting her
grandchildren, her son and her and his
do and her daughter-in-law and their
children. They live in LA. So she loves
seeing her grandchildren and she tries
to come off as she can. Well, Andrew
learns that she's actually owns a
business and and plans to, you know, buy
a business in the US. wants to spend
more time here, but she wants to kind of
grow her business. So, Andrew sets up a
meeting for her to talk about
opportunities here. And of course, she
eventually wants to probably be in the,
you know, Taiwan, move from Taiwan and
and maybe be a resident of the US
full-time to be next closer to her
family, but also running her business.
And she'll probably maintain a a
presence in Taiwan, which is fine. You
could certainly write her as a uh
non-resident, but once she moves to the
LA area, perfect. You can write her as a
resident and then it's even easier. So,
as Kathy said, we're here to support
your growth. Uh contact agency 1. Agency
one will will work with Lenny and
myself. Uh we're uh we we're you know,
this is really good business for us. We
have uh benchmarked ourselves against
the other carriers and so we've improved
many aspects of our uh uh strategy here
and you'll find that we're comparable if
not better than the other carriers in
this market. Hey Vente, we've got a
couple more questions and I encourage uh
everyone that's still attending if
you've got any questions please type
them into the Q&A. Uh the first question
was for a non-resident applicant who
owns property in the United States, does
the application have to be done in the
state where they own the property? It
has to be in their state where they have
the their residence or wherever that
property is. So if they own a pl a
property in Maryland, um you know, it
would make sense that you'd write the
application Maryland. You wouldn't write
it in California. Um, so, um, now the
underwriters, you know, this happens
with US business, right? Somebody's
visiting or maybe they're traveling and
you want to take the app. I think they
can work with you, but it has to be it
has to make sense, right, Kathy? It
can't be, well, I'm just on vacation in
California and I don't want to wait to
take the application till I get back to
Maryland. That's not a good enough
answer. Um, so usually we see them
writing the business where that person
has that property, that business, that
nexus.
Terrific. And another another question
is, can clients use a limited durable
power of attorney to deliver the policy
while the client is outside the United
States? Yeah, that was actually what I
was going to bring up, Kathy, is
sometimes your client comes and um maybe
they're here for a month or two and and
maybe the underwriting went longer and
the policies issued after they left.
That that has created problems in the
past, right? It's not, you know, you
don't want to wait for them to come back
and deliver it. So, if you know right up
front that they're going to be here for
a limited amount of time and um you know
there's a possibility that they may
actually be back in their home country
by the time the policy is issued, tell
us that upfront. you know, Lenny has a
process or with the company with our
underwriters. Well, he can let them know
upfront, hey, we need to exercise this
limited power of attorney because Andrew
is going to be back in Taiwan when the
policy's good possibility he'll be back
in Taiwan when the policyy's issued. You
got to tell us that, Kathy, upfront so
that way you can get the limited power
of attorney paperwork going, but you
can't tell us that right when you, well,
I found out yesterday Andrew, you know,
left for Taiwan and and I'm ready and I
want to deliver the policy next week.
That's not going to work. So, just tell
us upfront that that there's a
possibility or certainty that the
insured will be back in their home
country and then Lenny can get that
limited power of attorney uh going right
up front. And so, if you use it, great.
if you don't use it, you you had it. So,
it's a great question. That was one of
the things we improved upon from our old
system. We did not have the limited
power of attorney, but now we do.
Um, terrific. Uh, and then, uh, someone
else has asked, "What are the parameters
of who can be the limited power of
attorney?"
Well, um, it really up to you. Um,
usually that is, you know, you work with
that with your attorney. Um, in some
cases we've seen it be the spouse that's
here. Let's say the wife is traveling,
she's an executive, your writer, and
then by time, you know, it's delivered,
she's gone back to, you know, whatever
country, but the husband is here. Uh, in
some cases, you can have the husband
either be the LPOA or maybe even have
the husband be the policy owner. So,
there is some flexibility there, Kathy.
We just we know we need to deliver it to
someone in an official capacity. It just
can't be delivering it to somebody
arbitrary, right? Uh because then that
creates issues. So tell us upfront who
that you know who you're thinking about.
You get the uh you you know get with
Lenny and we get all the paperwork
going. Typically that limited power of
attorney involves meeting with your
attorney to get that kind of official.
Um but um you know if you let us know
upfront that that possibility, the whole
process goes much more smoothly. When it
comes to policy delivery, it certainly
has to be someone in some type of
connection to that insured, right? You
know, it can't be just some person off
the street that can't be the door man at
the building. Right. Right. The doorman
that takes your stuff and doesn't tell
you about it.
Okay. Um I don't think that we have any
other questions and we are nearing the
top of the hour. Uh, Vincente, do you
have any other closing comments before I
would just say the three the three
things to remember is one uh resident
alien business Kathy is easy business.
So I would say that's probably the
easiest thing for your uh for your
clients uh your producers um your team.
Secondly, when the non-resident comes
up, uh as Gonzalo pointed out, know what
country they're in. Find out that early
on in the process. uh if they're a AB or
one of these kind of mixed countries
then great. If they're a C or one of
these countries that's war torn and have
economic problems then you know that
that's kind of no-fly. And then the
third thing is just remember they have
to have some kind of nexus to the US.
Usually that $500,000 one is a total
asset to the US is easy either a house
or property. Um, and then if you have
those three things, then I think you're
much easier to go out and prospect the
business because you know what those
three requirements are.
Terrific. Thank you very much, Vicente.
This was terrific. Very informative. Uh,
I want to thank you. I want to thank
Lenny Paul, our uh, credential rep, who
is doing a yman's job on agency 1's
behalf. So, if anybody on the phone has
any questions, comments, or concerns
about their credential cases, please
reach out to us because uh Lenny is
doing a, as I said, a terrific job.
Before we close this webinar out, I'm
going to turn it over to Lisa Mitchell.
She's got a few announcements about some
upcoming webinars that I hope that our
attendees will be joining us for because
I think they will find them uh at least
as interesting as uh our what what our
friends from Credential did for us
today. So, Lisa,
Lisa, we can't hear you.
Can you hear me now? Yes. Good. You just
never know with these headsets. We've
got two more uh webinars for the month
of June scheduled right now. Um and I'll
be sending out uh updated lists or
webinar lists uh you know in the in the
coming weeks. But I believe next week
we've got one on June 12th at noon. Uh
it's uh feature or it's hosted by
Symmetra and it's a unique guaranteed
issue multilife program that uh that
Doug Bowen who is uh the director of
advanced markets will be discussing. And
then on June 24th, uh we've got Nate our
friends at Nationwide, uh at noon also,
uh they'll be discussing why affluent
clients need LTC and how to internally
split a 1035 exchange for better
purposes. And that's going to be our
friend uh Sean Britt uh discussing that.
Um and she is uh you know long-term care
in charge of long-term care initiatives
and advanced consulting group. And then
we've got one coming up in July, but
that's next month. So, we'll be
discussing that at another time. Uh, but
be looking for uh emails from me on uh
our upcoming webinars. And thanks a lot,
everyone. Okay. Thank you, Lisa. Again,
thank you uh to our friends uh at
Credential, Vicente, and Lenny. This was
terrific. On behalf of Gonzalo, Dennis
and myself, uh, Agency 1 is very
appreciative of your business and all of
the opportunities that we continue to
see from you. If you have any questions,
comments, or concerns, please reach out
to us. We are here to help you and look
forward to doing so. Thank you for
joining us. I hope everybody has a
terrific week and that we see you on the
next webinar. Thank you very much.